<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="/https://fazledyn.github.io/medusa-theme-jekyll/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/https://fazledyn.github.io/medusa-theme-jekyll/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-10-31T22:24:47+06:00</updated><id>/https://fazledyn.github.io/medusa-theme-jekyll/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Medusa</title><subtitle>Medusa is a child theme of Mundana Theme built on Jekyll</subtitle><entry xml:lang="bn"><title type="html">সাজেকাব্যর প্রথম খন্ড</title><link href="/https://fazledyn.github.io/medusa-theme-jekyll/sajekabbo-one/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="সাজেকাব্যর প্রথম খন্ড" /><published>2020-01-20T00:00:00+06:00</published><updated>2020-01-20T00:00:00+06:00</updated><id>/https://fazledyn.github.io/medusa-theme-jekyll/sajekabbo-one</id><content type="html" xml:base="/https://fazledyn.github.io/medusa-theme-jekyll/sajekabbo-one/">&lt;p&gt;আড়াই থেকে তিন ঘন্টা চান্দের গাড়িতে করে সাজেক পৌছাবার পর যখন সবাই রিসোর্টে ঢুকে আরাম করতেসে, কেউ কেউ আবার রিসোর্টের দোলনায় ঝুলতে ঝুলতে ছবি তুলছে। তখন আমি বের হলাম আমাদের রিসোর্টের রেস্টুরেন্টের খোঁজে। রিসোর্টের ম্যানেজার সোহেল ভাই বললো- আমাদের সাজেক ক্ল্যাসিক প্রিমিয়াম রিসোর্টের পাশেই রেস্টুরেন্ট, আর্মি পোস্ট হতে সামনে।&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ম্যাপে দেখলাম যে এখান থেকে কাছেই, হেটে যেতে তিন কিলোমিটারের মত হবে। আমি বেরিয়ে পড়লাম রেস্টুরেন্টের উদ্দেশ্যে, পিছনে দেখি উৎস ডাক দিলো সেও যাবে আমার সাথে।&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;একসাথে আমরা হাটা দিয়ে চলতে থাকলাম, প্রথমে এক কিলোমিটার, তারপর দেখলাম হেলিপ্যাড দুইটা। তার পরেই দেখি আর্মি পোস্ট। ভাবলাম- যাক এসেই পড়লাম, ম্যাপেও দেখায় মাত্র ১-১.৫ কিলোমিটারের মত। হেলিপ্যাড পাড় হবার পর পাকা রাস্তা শেষ- এবার মাটির আধা ভাঙা রাস্তা ধরেই আমরা চলতে থাকলাম, কথা বলতে বলতে। আর নিজেরা ভুল করে ফেললাম নাকি কোথাও সে বিষয়ে চিন্তা করতে করতে।&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;একসময় আমাদের রাস্তা শেষ হলো- তাকিয়ে দেখলাম একটা পাহাড় দাড়িয়ে আছে সামনে। বুঝতে বাকি রইলো না যে আমরা বোকচোদের মত ৩ কিলোমিটার হেটে হেটে কংলাক পাহাড়ের সামনে এসে পৌছে গেসি 😑  পাহাড়ের নিচে রাখা চান্দের গাড়ির স্ট্যান্ডে খেয়াল করলাম- মাকসুদকে। মাকসুদ হলো আমাদের চান্দের গাড়ির ড্রাইভার শরীফ ভাইয়ের সাগরেদ- সাজেকের ভাষায় যাদের “লাইনম্যান” নামে ডাকা হয়।&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ইতোমধ্যে শরীফ ভাইয়ের সাথেও দেখা হলো। উনি জিজ্ঞেস করলেন এখানে আমরা কী করতে আসছি আর কিভাবেই বা আসলাম। উনাকে আমাদের কান্ড কারখানা বলার পর উনি হেসে হেসে আমাদের বললেন যে, উনিও এখানে এক কাজে এসেছেন লোকজনের সাথে দেখা করতে। কাজ শেষ হলেই আমাদেরকে গাড়িতে করে রিসোর্টে নামিয়ে দিবেন।&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;পরে আমাদেরকে উনি এক দোকানে ইন্ডিয়ান গুড়া দুধের স্পেশাল চা খাওয়ালেন। তার আগে আমি আর উৎস এক বোতল করে এনার্জি ড্রিংক্স খেয়ে আমাদের সুগার ফিলাপ করলাম। চা খাওয়ার পর উনার সাথে ভালোই গল্প হল।&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;উনি গত ১৯ বছর যাবত ড্রাইভার হিসেবে কর্মরত আছেন। চান্দের গাড়ি থেকে শুরু করে বাস-ট্রাক পর্যন্ত সব চালিয়েছেন। এমনকি উনার টেকনাফ থেকে তেতুলিয়া ট্রাক চালাবার অভিজ্ঞতাও তিনি বর্ণনা করলেন। এবং সেই রুটে কোথায় কোথায় রেস্ট নিতে হয়, সেটার গল্পও করলেন।&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;আমাদের খোশগল্প শেষে আমরা চান্দের গাড়ির ছাদে উঠলাম এক্সপেরিয়েন্স নেয়ার জন্য। আঁকাবাকা- মাটির রাস্তা দিয়ে যাওয়ার সময় রোলার কোস্টারের যে অনুভূতি পেয়েছিলাম, তা বলার মত নয়। ৫ মিনিটের মধ্যে আমরা আমাদের রিসোর্টের সামনে হাজির।&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;এসে দেখি রিসোর্ট ফাকা- কোথাও কেও নেই&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="Jekyll" /><category term="tutorial" /><category term="tour" /><summary type="html">আড়াই থেকে তিন ঘন্টা চান্দের গাড়িতে করে সাজেক পৌছাবার পর যখন সবাই রিসোর্টে ঢুকে আরাম করতেসে, কেউ কেউ আবার রিসোর্টের দোলনায় ঝুলতে ঝুলতে ছবি তুলছে। তখন আমি বের হলাম আমাদের রিসোর্টের রেস্টুরেন্টের খোঁজে। রিসোর্টের ম্যানেজার সোহেল ভাই বললো- আমাদের সাজেক ক্ল্যাসিক প্রিমিয়াম রিসোর্টের পাশেই রেস্টুরেন্ট, আর্মি পোস্ট হতে সামনে।</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/https://fazledyn.github.io/medusa-theme-jekyll/assets/images/sajekabbo-1.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="/https://fazledyn.github.io/medusa-theme-jekyll/assets/images/sajekabbo-1.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">Relentless</title><link href="/https://fazledyn.github.io/medusa-theme-jekyll/relentless-eida/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Relentless" /><published>2019-10-05T00:00:00+06:00</published><updated>2019-10-05T00:00:00+06:00</updated><id>/https://fazledyn.github.io/medusa-theme-jekyll/relentless-eida</id><content type="html" xml:base="/https://fazledyn.github.io/medusa-theme-jekyll/relentless-eida/">&lt;p&gt;You eventually fall out of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a lot of people it’s just a getting into and out of. Blockbuster entertainment. You get a ticket, stand in line, look for your seat, sit through the action, get out go home go to sleep wake up go to work… You know the drill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I, on the other hand, am one of those nerds. Bro, I need to meditate before I go see a movie. I need to resonate with the vibes on the screen, you know? I don’t even get popcorn! Look, I don’t want the sound emanating from my own mouth to put me off, distract me from even one irrelevant line Emma fucking Stone would say to another eternal ga-ga loverboy archetype. It’s a disease: I’m a little too serious. It doesn’t make for good living in these times, bro.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think you can understand how it’s been the last few months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we hit it off I researched her. I had to know everything, about her, about me, about me with her, about us. We became a unit, an army, a nation. Every little thing that threatened to jeopardize our “usness” like fucking five years down the line I’d take care of it now. I adjusted so many of my bullshit for hers. Now, don’t get me wrong, I’m not saying she didn’t too, but it’s a stressful process man. And at one point you start being so much of this new you that you start forgetting what you used to be and the minutest of inconveniences makes you beg that same anxious question - was I better off by myself?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there’s no “I” now, bro. The subject cannot exist in a relationship. I fought through, every month, every week, and then every day. And then when she comes to tell you it’s over, well, you just shatter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;is-this-how-it-ends-&quot;&gt;Is this how it ends ?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went up to her one last time. It’s a blockbuster cliche, you know how it goes. The hero goes up to the heroine, she says no, he says “please”, she says no, yada-yada. I asked her if anything’s still there. Yeah, I know, it sounds desperate, but i really was desperate. Back against the wall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She was adamant. I respect that. I’ve been trying to get back ever since. To myself, on my feet, how it used to be, you know? It’s hard fucking work, man, but I’m giving it a shot.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="Jekyll" /><category term="tutorial" /><category term="summer" /><category term="featured" /><summary type="html">You eventually fall out of it.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/https://fazledyn.github.io/medusa-theme-jekyll/assets/images/eida-relentless.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="/https://fazledyn.github.io/medusa-theme-jekyll/assets/images/eida-relentless.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">Nightdriver - EIDA</title><link href="/https://fazledyn.github.io/medusa-theme-jekyll/nightdriver-eida/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Nightdriver - EIDA" /><published>2019-06-27T00:00:00+06:00</published><updated>2019-06-27T00:00:00+06:00</updated><id>/https://fazledyn.github.io/medusa-theme-jekyll/nightdriver-eida</id><content type="html" xml:base="/https://fazledyn.github.io/medusa-theme-jekyll/nightdriver-eida/">&lt;p&gt;From galaxies distant, our little city of Dhaka could look like a cluster of stars. There’s just so much light.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zoom in a little closer, it may look something like the back of a translucent butterfly floating over an abyss.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A little closer (like Google map close) and it’s a bonafide metropolitan! The sheer urbanity of the city night sky can spur intense political discussions about why we don’t rival New York or Paris already.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this is where you should stop it with the zooming. From this point onward, shit falls apart. The illuminated gridlines become insufferable gridlocks. The vibrance is exposed, the spirit is debunked. What is left is a city burnt out from overreaching itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zoom in any more and you get a taste of the real nightlife of this city. It’s you, a newlywed, sat on a public bus, 3 hours after your office closed. You’re sweating profusely, you have a 5-hour sleep to catch, and what’s supposed to be the best time of your life is just slipping away from your fingers. You just can’t take this anymore. Gggaaaaahhhhh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Someone get news out to the galaxies. We don’t want the lights to betray some innocent aliens into this speed trap. I mean, we still make do, but it’ll probably be pretty hard for someone to go from lightspeed to 4 km/h just like that.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="Jekyll" /><category term="tutorial" /><category term="sticky" /><summary type="html">From galaxies distant, our little city of Dhaka could look like a cluster of stars. There’s just so much light.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/https://fazledyn.github.io/medusa-theme-jekyll/assets/images/eida-nightdriver.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="/https://fazledyn.github.io/medusa-theme-jekyll/assets/images/eida-nightdriver.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">Welcome to Jekyll!</title><link href="/https://fazledyn.github.io/medusa-theme-jekyll/welcome-to-jekyll/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Welcome to Jekyll!" /><published>2019-02-04T00:00:00+06:00</published><updated>2019-02-04T00:00:00+06:00</updated><id>/https://fazledyn.github.io/medusa-theme-jekyll/welcome-to-jekyll</id><content type="html" xml:base="/https://fazledyn.github.io/medusa-theme-jekyll/welcome-to-jekyll/">&lt;p&gt;You’ll find this post in your &lt;code class=&quot;language-html highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;_posts&lt;/code&gt; directory. Go ahead and edit it and re-build the site to see your changes. You can rebuild the site in many different ways, but the most common way is to run &lt;code class=&quot;language-html highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;jekyll serve&lt;/code&gt;, which launches a web server and auto-regenerates your site when a file is updated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To add new posts, simply add a file in the &lt;code class=&quot;language-html highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;_posts&lt;/code&gt; directory that follows the convention &lt;code class=&quot;language-html highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;YYYY-MM-DD-name-of-post.ext&lt;/code&gt; and includes the necessary front matter. Take a look at the source for this post to get an idea about how it works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jekyll also offers powerful support for code snippets:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-ruby&quot; data-lang=&quot;ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;print_hi&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;puts&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;Hi, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;si&quot;&gt;#{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;si&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;print_hi&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;'Tom'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;#=&amp;gt; prints 'Hi, Tom' to STDOUT.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out the &lt;a href=&quot;https://jekyllrb.com/docs/home&quot;&gt;Jekyll docs&lt;/a&gt; for more info on how to get the most out of Jekyll. File all bugs/feature requests at &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jekyll/jekyll&quot;&gt;Jekyll’s GitHub repo&lt;/a&gt;. If you have questions, you can ask them on &lt;a href=&quot;https://talk.jekyllrb.com/&quot;&gt;Jekyll Talk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="Jekyll" /><summary type="html">You’ll find this post in your _posts directory. Go ahead and edit it and re-build the site to see your changes. You can rebuild the site in many different ways, but the most common way is to run jekyll serve, which launches a web server and auto-regenerates your site when a file is updated.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/https://fazledyn.github.io/medusa-theme-jekyll/assets/images/demo1.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="/https://fazledyn.github.io/medusa-theme-jekyll/assets/images/demo1.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">Powerful things you can do with the Markdown editor</title><link href="/https://fazledyn.github.io/medusa-theme-jekyll/powerful-things-markdown-editor/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Powerful things you can do with the Markdown editor" /><published>2019-02-03T00:00:00+06:00</published><updated>2019-02-03T00:00:00+06:00</updated><id>/https://fazledyn.github.io/medusa-theme-jekyll/powerful-things-markdown-editor</id><content type="html" xml:base="/https://fazledyn.github.io/medusa-theme-jekyll/powerful-things-markdown-editor/">&lt;p&gt;There are lots of powerful things you can do with the Markdown editor. If you’ve gotten pretty comfortable with writing in Markdown, then you may enjoy some more advanced tips about the types of things you can do with Markdown!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As with the last post about the editor, you’ll want to be actually editing this post as you read it so that you can see all the Markdown code we’re using.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;special-formatting&quot;&gt;Special formatting&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As well as bold and italics, you can also use some other special formatting in Markdown when the need arises, for example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;del&gt;strike through&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;==highlight==&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;*escaped characters*&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;writing-code-blocks&quot;&gt;Writing code blocks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two types of code elements which can be inserted in Markdown, the first is inline, and the other is block. Inline code is formatted by wrapping any word or words in back-ticks, &lt;code class=&quot;language-html highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;like this&lt;/code&gt;. Larger snippets of code can be displayed across multiple lines using triple back ticks:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-html highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;syntax&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;.my-link {
    text-decoration: underline;
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to get really fancy, you can even add syntax highlighting using Rouge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://fazledyn.github.io/medusa-theme-jekyll//assets/images/8.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;walking&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;reference-lists&quot;&gt;Reference lists&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The quick brown jumped over the lazy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another way to insert links in markdown is using reference lists. You might want to use this style of linking to cite reference material in a Wikipedia-style. All of the links are listed at the end of the document, so you can maintain full separation between content and its source or reference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;full-html&quot;&gt;Full HTML&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the best part of Markdown is that you’re never limited to just Markdown. You can write HTML directly in the Markdown editor and it will just work as HTML usually does. No limits! Here’s a standard YouTube embed code as an example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe style=&quot;width:100%;&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Cniqsc9QfDo?rel=0&amp;amp;showinfo=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="Jekyll" /><category term="tutorial" /><category term="summer" /><summary type="html">There are lots of powerful things you can do with the Markdown editor. If you’ve gotten pretty comfortable with writing in Markdown, then you may enjoy some more advanced tips about the types of things you can do with Markdown!</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://images.unsplash.com/photo-1528784351875-d797d86873a1?ixlib=rb-1.2.1&amp;auto=format&amp;fit=crop&amp;w=750&amp;q=80" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://images.unsplash.com/photo-1528784351875-d797d86873a1?ixlib=rb-1.2.1&amp;auto=format&amp;fit=crop&amp;w=750&amp;q=80" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">The first mass-produced book to deviate from a rectilinear format</title><link href="/https://fazledyn.github.io/medusa-theme-jekyll/first-mass-produced/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The first mass-produced book to deviate from a rectilinear format" /><published>2019-02-02T00:00:00+06:00</published><updated>2019-02-02T00:00:00+06:00</updated><id>/https://fazledyn.github.io/medusa-theme-jekyll/first-mass-produced</id><content type="html" xml:base="/https://fazledyn.github.io/medusa-theme-jekyll/first-mass-produced/">&lt;p&gt;The first mass-produced book to deviate from a rectilinear format, at least in the United States, is thought to be this 1863 edition of Red Riding Hood, cut into the shape of the protagonist herself with the troublesome wolf curled at her feet. Produced by the Boston-based publisher Louis Prang, this is the first in their “Doll Series”, a set of five “die-cut” books, known also as shape books — the other titles being Robinson Crusoe, Goody Two-Shoes (also written by Red Riding Hood author Lydia Very), Cinderella, and King Winter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An 1868 Prang catalogue would later claim that such “books in the shape of a regular paper Doll… originated with us”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It would seem the claim could also extend to die cut books in general, as we can’t find anything sooner, but do let us know in the comments if you have further light to shed on this! Such books are, of course, still popular in children’s publishing today, though the die cutting is not now limited to mere outlines, as evidenced in a beautiful 2014 version of the same Little Red Riding Hood story.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The die cut has also been employed in the non-juvenile sphere as well, a recent example being Jonathan Safran Foer’s ambitious Tree of Codes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for this particular rendition of Charles Perrault’s classic tale, the text and design is by Lydia Very (1823-1901), sister of Transcendentalist poet Jones Very. The gruesome ending of the original - which sees Little Red Riding Hood being gobbled up as well as her grandmother - is avoided here, the gore giving way to the less bloody aims of the morality tale, and the lesson that one should not disobey one’s mother.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To deviate from a rectilinear format, at least in the United States, is thought to be this 1863 edition of Red Riding Hood, cut into the shape of the protagonist herself with the troublesome wolf curled at her feet. Produced by the Boston-based publisher Louis Prang, this is the first in their “Doll Series”, a set of five “die-cut” books, known also as shape books — the other titles being Robinson Crusoe, Goody Two-Shoes (also written by Red Riding Hood author Lydia Very), Cinderella, and King Winter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An 1868 Prang catalogue would later claim that such “books in the shape of a regular paper Doll… originated with us”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The claim could also extend to die cut books in general, as we can’t find anything sooner, but do let us know in the comments if you have further light to shed on this! Such books are, of course, still popular in children’s publishing today, though the die cutting is not now limited to mere outlines, as evidenced in a beautiful 2014 version of the same Little Red Riding Hood story.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The die cut has also been employed in the non-juvenile sphere as well, a recent example being Jonathan Safran Foer’s ambitious Tree of Codes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for this particular rendition of Charles Perrault’s classic tale, the text and design is by Lydia Very (1823-1901), sister of Transcendentalist poet Jones Very. The gruesome ending of the original - which sees Little Red Riding Hood being gobbled up as well as her grandmother - is avoided here, the gore giving way to the less bloody aims of the morality tale, and the lesson that one should not disobey one’s mother.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="tutorial" /><category term="featured" /><summary type="html">The first mass-produced book to deviate from a rectilinear format, at least in the United States, is thought to be this 1863 edition of Red Riding Hood, cut into the shape of the protagonist herself with the troublesome wolf curled at her feet. Produced by the Boston-based publisher Louis Prang, this is the first in their “Doll Series”, a set of five “die-cut” books, known also as shape books — the other titles being Robinson Crusoe, Goody Two-Shoes (also written by Red Riding Hood author Lydia Very), Cinderella, and King Winter.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/https://fazledyn.github.io/medusa-theme-jekyll/assets/images/17.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="/https://fazledyn.github.io/medusa-theme-jekyll/assets/images/17.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">Markdown Example</title><link href="/https://fazledyn.github.io/medusa-theme-jekyll/markup-example/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Markdown Example" /><published>2019-01-19T00:00:00+06:00</published><updated>2019-01-19T00:00:00+06:00</updated><id>/https://fazledyn.github.io/medusa-theme-jekyll/markup-example</id><content type="html" xml:base="/https://fazledyn.github.io/medusa-theme-jekyll/markup-example/">&lt;p&gt;You’ll find this post in your &lt;code class=&quot;language-html highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;_posts&lt;/code&gt; directory. Go ahead and edit it and re-build the site to see your changes. You can rebuild the site in many different ways, but the most common way is to run &lt;code class=&quot;language-html highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;jekyll serve&lt;/code&gt;, which launches a web server and auto-regenerates your site when a file is updated. Something.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To add new posts, simply add a file in the &lt;code class=&quot;language-html highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;_posts&lt;/code&gt; directory that follows the convention &lt;code class=&quot;language-html highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;YYYY-MM-DD-name-of-post.ext&lt;/code&gt; and includes the necessary front matter. Take a look at the source for this post to get an idea about how it works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jekyll also offers powerful support for code snippets:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-python&quot; data-lang=&quot;python&quot;&gt;&lt;table class=&quot;rouge-table&quot;&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;gutter gl&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;lineno&quot;&gt;1
2
3
4
5
6
7
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;code&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kn&quot;&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nn&quot;&gt;os&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;environ&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;kn&quot;&gt;from&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nn&quot;&gt;flask&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kn&quot;&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Flask&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;app&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Flask&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;__name__&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;==&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;__main__&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;app&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;run&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out the &lt;a href=&quot;http://jekyllrb.com/docs/home&quot;&gt;Jekyll docs&lt;/a&gt; for more info on how to get the most out of Jekyll. File all bugs/feature requests at &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jekyll/jekyll&quot;&gt;Jekyll’s GitHub repo&lt;/a&gt;. If you have questions, you can ask them on &lt;a href=&quot;https://talk.jekyllrb.com/&quot;&gt;Jekyll Talk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="Jekyll" /><category term="tutorial" /><category term="featured" /><summary type="html">You’ll find this post in your _posts directory. Go ahead and edit it and re-build the site to see your changes. You can rebuild the site in many different ways, but the most common way is to run jekyll serve, which launches a web server and auto-regenerates your site when a file is updated. Something.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/https://fazledyn.github.io/medusa-theme-jekyll/assets/images/6.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="/https://fazledyn.github.io/medusa-theme-jekyll/assets/images/6.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry xml:lang="bn"><title type="html">বাংলা কাস্টম ফন্ট উদাহরণ</title><link href="/https://fazledyn.github.io/medusa-theme-jekyll/bengali-elegant-font-example/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="বাংলা কাস্টম ফন্ট উদাহরণ" /><published>2019-01-18T00:00:00+06:00</published><updated>2019-01-18T00:00:00+06:00</updated><id>/https://fazledyn.github.io/medusa-theme-jekyll/bengali-elegant-font-example</id><content type="html" xml:base="/https://fazledyn.github.io/medusa-theme-jekyll/bengali-elegant-font-example/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;অর্থহীন-লেখা&quot;&gt;অর্থহীন লেখা&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;অর্থহীন লেখা যার মাঝে আছে অনেক কিছু। হ্যাঁ, এই লেখার মাঝেই আছে অনেক কিছু। যদি তুমি মনে করো, এটা তোমার কাজে লাগবে, তাহলে তা লাগবে কাজে। নিজের ভাষায় লেখা দেখতে অভ্যস্ত হও। মনে রাখবে লেখা অর্থহীন হয়, যখন তুমি তাকে অর্থহীন মনে করো; আর লেখা অর্থবোধকতা তৈরি করে, যখন তুমি তাতে অর্থ ঢালো। যেকোনো লেখাই তোমার কাছে অর্থবোধকতা তৈরি করতে পারে, যদি তুমি সেখানে অর্থদ্যোতনা দেখতে পাও। … ছিদ্রান্বেষণ? না, তা হবে কেন?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;যে কথাকে কাজে লাগাতে চাও, তাকে কাজে লাগানোর কথা চিন্তা করার আগে ভাবো, তুমি কি সেই কথার জাদুতে আচ্ছন্ন হয়ে গেছ কিনা। তুমি যদি নিশ্চিত হও যে, তুমি কোনো মোহাচ্ছাদিত আবহে আবিষ্ট হয়ে অন্যের শেখানো বুলি আত্মস্থ করছো না, তাহলে তুমি নির্ভয়ে, নিশ্চিন্তে অগ্রসর হও। তুমি সেই কথাকে জানো, বুঝো, আত্মস্থ করো; মনে রাখবে, যা অনুসরণ করতে চলেছো, তা আগে অনুধাবন করা জরুরি; এখানে কিংকর্তব্যবিমূঢ় হবার কোনো সুযোগ নেই।&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;কোনো কথা শোনামাত্রই কি তুমি তা বিশ্বাস করবে? হয়তো বলবে, করবে, হয়তো বলবে “আমি করবো না।” হ্যা, “আমি করবো না” বললেই সবকিছু অস্বীকার করা যায় না, হয়তো তুমি মনের গহীন গভীর থেকে ঠিকই বিশ্বাস করতে শুরু করেছো সেই কথাটি, কিন্তু মুখে অস্বীকার করছো। তাই সচেতন থাকো, তুমি কী ভাবছো— তার প্রতি; সচেতন থাকো, তুমি কি আসলেই বিশ্বাস করতে চলেছো ঐ কথাটি… শুধু এতটুকু বলি, যা-ই বিশ্বাস করো না কেন, আগে যাচাই করে নাও; আর এতে চাই তোমার প্রত্যুৎপন্নমতিত্ব।&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;তাই কোন কথাটি কাজে লাগবে, তা নির্ধারণ করবে তুমি— হ্যাঁ, তুমি। হয়তো সামান্য ক’টা বাংলা অক্ষর: খন্ড-ত, অনুস্বার, বিঃসর্গ কিংবা চন্দ্রবিন্দু— কিন্তু যদি তুমি বিশ্বাস করো, তাহলে হয়তো তুমি তা দিয়েই তৈরি করতে পারো এক উচ্চমার্গীয় মহাকাব্য- এক চিরসবুজ অর্ঘ্য। রচিত হতে পারে পৃথিবীর ১ম বিরাম চিহ্নের ইতিকথা – এক নতুন ঊষা। …মহাকাব্য লিখতে ঋষি-মুনি হওয়া লাগে না।
অর্থহীনতা আর অর্থদ্যোতনার সেই ঈর্ষাকাতর মোহাবিষ্টতা তাই তৈরি করে নাও নিজের মাঝে- চাই একটুখানি ঔৎসুক্য। নিজেই ঠিক করো, নিজের ভাষাটা কি অর্থহীন, নাকি কিছু সত্যিই বলছে!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="Jekyll" /><category term="tutorial" /><summary type="html">অর্থহীন লেখা</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/https://fazledyn.github.io/medusa-theme-jekyll/assets/images/11.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="/https://fazledyn.github.io/medusa-theme-jekyll/assets/images/11.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>